本字幕由YYeTs人人影视字幕翻译制作
更多字幕 影视 请登陆 www.YYeTs.net
翻译： halg   pckuang   running703   chenshaner
校对：  小的瑟  字幕总监：lonelyatta  梁良
我还在问自已是否做的对
I still ask myself if I did the right thing
当我离开了他漂泊的城市
when I abandoned his floating city
我指的不仅是工作
And I don't mean only for the work
事实是  那样才是真正的朋友
fact is, a friend like that a real friend
你再也不会见到他这样的人
you won't meet one again
如果你不想出海
If you just decide to hang up your sea legs
如果你只想站在陆地上
if you just want to feel something more solid beneath your feet
如果你不再想听见天籁之音
and if then you no loner hear the music of the gods around you
但是  像他常说过的一样
But, like he used to say
只要你有个好故事  你就永远不会被人忘记
You're never really done for as long as you got a good story
一个值得告诉别人的故事
and someone to tell it to
可问题是
Trouble is
没人相信我的故事
nobody'd believe a single word of my story
每次都是这样
It happened every time
某人一抬头就看到她
Someone would look up and see her
很难理解
It's difficult to understand
那船上有上千人
There'd be more than a thousand of us on that ship
有富人  移民  陌生人和我们
Traveling rich folks, immigrants and strange people, and us
但是总会有一个人
Yet there was always one
一眼就看到她的单身汉
One guy alone who would see her first
或许他只是坐在那吃东西或是在甲板上散步
Maybe he was just sitting there eating or walking on the deck
或许他正在缝补裤子
Maybe he was just fixing his pants
他抬起头  很快地向海上望去  便看到了她
He'd look up for a second. A quick glance out to sea and he'd see her
他的脚像生了根  心也悸动不安
Then he'd just stand there rooted to the spot, his heart racing
每次  每一次  我发誓
And every time every damn time, I swear
他转向我  冲着船朝着每个人大喊
he'd turn to us, towards the ship towards everybody and scream
美国
America
海上钢琴家
The Legend of 1900
纽约
New York
先看到美国的人
The one who sees America first
每个船上都有一个
There's one on every ship
不要以为这是偶然
And don't be thinking it's an accident
或是视觉幻想  那是命运
Or some optical illusion It's destiny
这些人
Those are people who always
在他们的生命中都是有印记的
have that precise instant stamped on their life
当他们是孩子的时候你看他们眼睛
And when they were kids you could look into their eyes
如果你仔细观察你就会看到她
and if you looked carefully enough you'd already see her
美国
America
我没见过多少美国人
And I've seen a few Americas
呆在那船上六年
Six years on that ship five crossings a year
一年横跨五次欧洲和美国
Europe, America and back always soaking in the ocean
当你踏上大陆
When you stepped on land
你在上厕所的时候都会感觉晃
you couldn't even piss straight in the john
我的意思是  厕所是不动的
It was teady. The john, I mean
你却像个白痴一样不停的晃
But you'd keep bobbing like an idiot
你可以安然无恙的离开船  但是却不可能离开大海
You can get off a ship all right But off the ocean
马上要关门了
I was just closing
需要点什么
What can I do for you?
当我登上这船的时候才24岁
When I boarded, I was 24 years old
一生中我只在乎一件事
And I only cared about one thing in life
演奏小号
Playing the trumpet
我要卖这个
I'm selling it
康恩
Conn
不错
Not bad
黄铜是最好的
Best brass money can buy
最高出六磅七先令
Six pounds, ten shillings Best I can do
先生  这是我的全部
That horn's my whole life, mister
即使我不是什么名人
Even being a nobody
至少也值20美元
has got to be worth more than twenty lousy bucks
事情就是这样  我认为连二先令都不值
It that's how things are, I suppose it's barely worth half a crown
走后请关门
Shut the door when you leave please
好吧  老爹
Okay, pops
你赢了
you win
你刚买了一部分音乐史
You just bought yourself a piece of musical history
如果你想要我的建议
Now if you want my advice
去吃顿好的
go out, treat yourself to a decent meal
至少让我在吹一次
At least let me play it one last time
我没有时间
Young man I don't have time to waste
好吧
All right
那就快点
Hurry up, then
要关门了
I'm closing
谢谢
Thank you
这样才完美  你说呢
Two peas in a pod, wouldn't you say
这是你刚才吹的那段音乐
It's the music you were just playing
叫什么
What is it?
没有名字
It doesn't have a name
只有少数人听过
Just a handful of people have had the privilege of hearing it
这种曲风  今天早上我就在想
That style. I was wondering since this morning, but...
我不认识这个出神入化的钢琴师
I can't work out who this amazing piano player is
我想你从来没听说过他
I don't think you ever heard of him
他是谁
Who is he?
如果我告诉你这个钢琴师从来不存在
If I told you this pianist never existed
我没说谎
I wouldn't be lying
我不喜欢秘密
I don't like secrets
快点  美国佬  这人是谁
Come on now, Yank who the devil is playing?
那是我的秘密
That's my secret
那是这个该死的世纪的第一年
It was the first year of this frigging century
被一个弗吉尼亚不知名的黑人煤矿工命名的
as defined by an unknown colored coal stoker on the Virginian
该死的有钱人  什么都没留下
Fucking rich-ass bastards Can't lose nothing
除了烟头和脏兮兮的手帕
but cigarette butts and dirty-ass handkerchiefs
就不能丢块手表
Can't lose no watch
或是旧的大理石或手链
not even a beat-up Elgin or a sorry-ass cufflink
我在说什么  连假戒指都没有
What am I talking about? Not even a fake fucking ring
看看这
Look here
一根烟
A whole cigar
一定是某个可怜人的
Must've been somebody poor at the party
看看这垃圾
Look at this shit
肮脏的白痴
Nasty fucker
该死的有钱人  除非他们欠你钱否则不会给你留下什么
Damn rich. Don't forget nothing unless they owe you some money
你这小家伙在这干嘛
What in the scuts you doing here?
"T.D. 雷蒙斯"
"T.D. Lemons"
你好 雷蒙
Howdy do there, Lemon
移民的混蛋
Immigrant bastard
你说对了  这就是移人应该做的
You said it That's the way the immigrants do it
有一个婴儿在船上
Have a baby on the ship
留下了一个活口需要喂养
and then leave on board another mouth to feed
这样可以避免移民局找麻烦
And, like that, avoid trouble with the immigration office
这样的孩子长大了会干什么
What's a boy like him going to be when he grows up?
成为另一个移民
Another immigrant
不用理这些混蛋  雷蒙
Don't pay those bastards no mind Lemon
来吧  喝吧
Go on, lap it up, boy
这个孩子被遗弃在头等舱的钢琴上
This one they left in first class on top the piano
他们希望有钱人能来
They are hoping some rich guy will come
给他喂个金勺子
and stick a silver spoon in his mouth
然而谁捡到了这个孩子呢
And who does the little ape get instead?
一个穷煤矿工
A poor coal stoker
有人把你当奶妈了  丹尼
Someoe is taking you for a sucker, Danny
他们快乐了  你却痛苦了
They have the fun You have the misery
该死的穷人
Fuck poverty
你们这些讨厌的褐家鼠
You stinking sewer rats
T.D 写在那个盒子上  你们这帮白痴知道那是什么意思嘛
T.D. was wrote on that box. Any of you shitheads know what that means?
我忘了  你们都不识字
I forgot. You all can't read
意思就是  谢谢丹尼  谢谢丹尼
It means, "Thanks, Danny." "Thanks, Danny"
他们是给我留着的  我要把他养大
They left him for me and I'm gonna keep him
你们去死吧
Rest of you all can go fuck yourselves
丹尼  你打算给他叫他什么
Danny, what are you going to call the nino?
该死  我没想到这个
Hell, I ain't think about that
我打算以我的名字命名
To start off I'm going to name him after me
丹尼 博德曼
Danny Boodman
T.D. 是中间名
Then I'll put "T.D." in the middle
就像富人放在中间一样  你们说呢
Iike rich folks puts that in the middle, don't you think?
把名字放在中间他就是个富人了  你们觉的怎么样
That give it class, to put that in the middle, don't you think?
所有的律师都有中间名字
All fucking lawyers gots initials in the middle of their names
我的律师叫乔纳森 PTK 旺德
Well, my lawyer was Jonathan PTK Wonder
如果我的孩子长大了是个律师我发誓我会亲手杀了他
My son grow up to be a lawyer I swear I'll kill him myself
但是孩子的名字还是会叫丹尼 博德曼 T.D・雷蒙
But the boy's name is still going to be Danny Boodman T.D. Lemon
他不是没爹的孩子丹尼
He ain't the son of no fucking duke, Danny
你在星期二发现他的就应该叫他星期二
You found him on a Tuesday Call him "Tuesday"
你不像看起来那么笨
You ain't as dumb as you look colored boy
我在这个该死的新世纪
I found him the first month
的第一年第一个月里发现了他
of the first year of this frigging new century
所以我叫他1900
So I calls him: Nineteen Hundred
1900?  但那是个数字
Nineteen Hundred? But that's a number
曾经是数字  但现在是个名字
It was a number, now it's a name
丹尼 博德曼 T.D・雷蒙　1900
Danny Boodman T.D. Lemon Nineteen Hundred
丹尼  你的婴儿不高兴了
Danny, your little bambino is not so happy
快点  快点  别怕  你妈妈来了
Come on, hurry. Hurry up Don't worry, your mama's here
该死  这么个小东西怎么拉这么多
Damn. How can something that small shit so much?
这就是1900怎么样长大的
And that's how little Nineteen Hundred grew up
在一个像船一样大的摇篮里
Inside that cradle as big as a shi
但自从丹尼怕他们由于一些商业
But since Danny was afraid they'd take him away
文件和签证就把他带走
on account of some business concerning documents and visas
因此他童年时
the boy lived his early years
总是躲在弗吉尼亚号船舱里
always hiding in the belly of the Virginian
好  现在你自已试试
Okay, now try one for yourself
用你的手指头按着这些文字
Put your finger up here against these words
这样字母就不会跑掉
so the letters can't run off on you
人
"Man"
不错  继续
All right, keep going
走
"Go"
继续
Go on
妈
"Ma"
在多说一点
Just a little bit more
妈
"Ma"
孩子  你读的真好  雷蒙
Boy, you read like a god, Lemon
继续  把他们连起来读
Now go on, put them all together
就像蒸气阀一样
kind of like them boiler valves Come on
芒...果...妈妈
"Man... go...Mama"
芒果妈妈  不错  继续
Mango Mama. All right. Deep going
美国佬  我的  手烤
Yank...My...Chain
丹尼, 你为什么觉的这么好笑
Danny, why are you laughing so much
因为这些是马的名字  你不觉的好笑嘛
Because these are names of horses Don't that make you laugh?
我只是很喜欢这些马的名字  看看这个
I"m just crazy about these horses' names. Look at this one here
高兴的舞蹈家
"Happy Hoofers"
听听这个
Listen to this
时髦的少女
"Sassy Lassy"
这个
And this one
泼辣妈妈
"Red Hot Mama"
丹尼, 妈妈是什么
What's a mama, Danny?
妈妈
A mama?
妈妈是一种马
A mama's a horse
一种马
A horse?
赛马
Racehorse
事实上  妈妈是世上最好的马
Matter of fact, you know what I say Mama's the best horse in the world?
如果你在一个纯种的妈妈马上下注  你总会赢
Thoroughbred You bet on a mama, you always win
塔诺・迪・阿马托
"Tano D'Amato
雷蒙斯国王
The King of Lemons"
爸爸  把你的手放在这读
Dad, put your finger here and read
T.D. 不是谢谢丹尼的意思
T.D. doesn't mean "Thanks, Danny"
这个变态是谁
Who's this pansy ass?
今晚就读这些吧
That's enough reading for tonight
读太多了对你来说不好
Too much reading is bad for you
还有什么不好  丹尼
What else is bad, Danny?
弗吉尼亚船下的一切都是不好的
Everything off the Virginian is bad
一切
Everything
陆地上有鲨鱼会活吃你
They got sharks on the land they eat you alive
离他们远点  听见了嘛
You keep away from they, you hear?
丹尼  什么是孤儿院
Danny, what's an orphanage?
孤儿院就像一个大的监狱
Well, a orphanage is like a great big prison
没孩子的人都会被关在里面
where they lock up folks that ain't got kids
如果我不和你在一起你就会进孤儿院嘛
So if I wasn't with you they would put you in an orphanage?
你说的对  小雷蒙
You got that right, little Lemon
晚安
Night-night
小心点  丹尼
Watch out, Danny
把他翻过来  把他翻过来
Roll over. Roll him over
我的天  医生
My God. Doctor
快叫医生  快叫医生
Call the doctor. Get the doctor
丹尼  你流血了  跟我说话
Danny, you bloody cow. Talk to me
没什么大事  就像个蚊子一样
Ain't nothing but a pat on the back, boys
该死
"Holy Shoot...
时间正好
and Times Were Good
没有权限
was disqualified
漂亮的小牛
"Saucy Bossy"
他挺了三天才死去  老丹尼
It took him three days to go toes up, old Danny
他下葬那天"饮用水"第六次在芝加哥获胜
He let go on the sixth race in Chicago
超过了"菜汤"两个身位
Drinkable Water by two lengths over Vegetable Soup
超过了"蓝基金"五个身位
and five over Blue Foudation
是的  我走过了死亡阴影的峡谷
"Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death
我不会怕身边的魔鬼
I will fear no evil for Thou art with me
你的朋友们照顾我
Thy rod and Thy staff they comfort me"
谢谢丹尼
"Thanks Danny"
以父亲和儿子以及圣灵的名义
In the name of the Father and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost
阿门
Amen
音乐
Music
1900那时候才八岁
Nineteen Hundred was eight years old then
他在欧洲和美国之间旅行
He'd made the trip between Europe and America
我猜大概有五十次
about fifty times, I imagine
大海就是他的家
The ocean was his home
他从来没有到过陆地
He never set foot on dry land Never
尽量他在港口看过很多次
Though he'd seen it from the ports a hundred times
但他从来没有下过船
But he never got off the boat
问题是
Problem was
世上没人知道他的存在
as far as the world was concerned he didn't even exist
没有一个城市  一个教会  一个医院  监狱或棒球队
There wasn't a city, a parish a hospital, jail or baseball team
知道他的名字
that had his name any place
他没有国籍  他没有生日  没有家人
He didn't have a country, he didn't even have a birth date. No family
他八岁了
He was eight years old but officially
但是官方却没有他出生的纪录
he had never even been born
禁止通行
"No Entry"
船长  船长  醒醒
Captain. Captain, wake up
他叫什么名字
What's his name?
Nineteen Hundred
不是歌名  那孩子的名
Not the song, the boy
Nineteen Hundred
像这曲子一样
Like the song
1900  这一切都违背常规
Nineteen Hundred, all of this is entirely against the regulations
该死的常规
Fuck the regulations
但是我不明白
But I don't understand
这和这个唱片有什么关系
what the record has to do with any of this
这个唱片不应该存在
This record shouldn't exist
唯一存在的混音唱片在被剪断后就被销毁了
The only existing matrix was destroyed right after it was cut
这就是原版
This is a matrix
听起来像是
Quite handy for on-the-spot recordings
现场录制的版本
that sort of business
你怎么能用手去碰它
How did you get your hands on this?
我花了不少时间
I spend the better part of the day
把碎片拼在一起
putting the bits and pieces together
我发现它纯属偶然
I found them by accident.
就藏在那架钢琴中
Hidden inside one of those two pianos
我从一个二手商那买到的
I bought them from a second-hand dealer
他们正在普利茅斯
They've emptied out an old hospital ship
拆一艘医疗船
at Plymouth
老兄  在那边
It's over there, mate
慢点  别那么快
Slow down not so fast with that pulley
小心一点
Easy up there, easy
小心点  这可不是香蕉
Watch that! These aren't bananas, you know
-你从哪来  -利物浦
-Where are you from?  -Liverpool
-工作呢  -理发师
-What do you do?  -I'm a barber
-录取  -非常感谢
-Sign him on -Thanks very much
下一个 你是干什么的
Next. What's your trade?
我是木匠  非常好的技师
I'm a carpenter. A good mechanic
滚出去
Get out
你的工作是
What do you do?
演奏小号
I play the trumpet
船上已经有乐师了  下一个
We've already got musicians on board. Next
他要去干嘛
Where the hell is he going?
-什么曲子 -我不知道
What's that? I don't know
你怎么能不知道 是爵士乐
When you don't know what it is it's jazz
这是我生命中最快乐的日子
It was the happiest day of my life
人们的眼中充满了希望
All those people hope in their eyes
道别声 汽笛声
The goodbyes, the sirens
这个漂浮的世界开始了它的旅程
And that big floating world starting to move
我觉得这是为我举办的
It felt like one big party A huge bash
盛大的派对
just for me
但是三天后
But just three days later
大海厌倦了欢乐
the ocean got tired of the festivities
康恩
Hey, Conn?
你没事吧
What's the matter?
晕船了？
Lose your sea legs?
你是不是新来的小号手
YOu're the new trumpet man aren't you?
用康恩牌小号的
And you blow a Conn
让我来减轻你的痛苦
Come with me I have a cure for your misery
跟我来
Follow me
请把保护松掉
Take the brakes off, please
你疯了
That's crazy
相信我  把保护松掉
Trust me. Just take the brakes off
坐到我边上来
Hop on next to me
你是什么人 疯子吗
What are you, some kind of nut case
你最好快点 要不上不来了
You better get on now or you never will
告诉我 你有小孩吗
Tell me something do you have children?
这种天气
They'll lock you up
小孩会被锁在孤儿院的
in the orphanage one of these days
他疯了
He's nuts
妈呀
Oh, mama
看得出来你喜欢赛马
I see you know your horses
还好啦
Just a litte
不错
Good man
晚上好 船长
Good evening, Captain
您要不要试一下
Care for a ride?
再说一遍那窗子他妈的有多大
Tell me again how big the fucking window was
那窗子可真他妈大
It was a big fucking window
我们会在这
We're going to be shoveling coal
永远的铲下去
on this ship till eternity
操
No shit
至少要等你知道
Least you know
长大了该干什么
what you'll be doing when you grow up
康恩
Conn
你是不是新奥尔良人
You're from New Orleans, right?
你怎么知道
How'd you know that?
我喜欢那个地方
I love that town
真的吗  我有一段时间没回去了
Really? I haven't been there in a while?
冬天的时候  漂亮极了
In winter, it's beautiful
三月份
And in March
你总能碰到那样的午后
you can always count on one afternoon
至少可以想像一下
when you least expect it
浓雾滑入
the fog slides in
就像白色的栅栏
a milky barrier
漂浮在街灯下
hangs just below the street lamps
淹没了万物
It cuts everything off
就像白色的刀  太神奇了
Iike a white blade. And it's magic
看不见房顶
Houses lose their top floors
看不见树枝
trees lose their branches
看不见圣路易斯教堂的尖塔
St. Louis Cathedral loses its spires
人们擦肩而过却互不相见
People passing by they lose their heads
脖子以上都消失了
So from the neck up everything disappears
你能在杰克森广场上碰到
All you can see in Jackson Square
人们像无头苍蝇一样到处乱闯
is decapitated bodies stumbling around
撞到谁就问
bumping into each other saying
“你家人呢”
"How's your mama and them?"
就是那样 太糟了 不过不会很久
That's it Too bad it doesn't last long
你怎么知道这些
How do you know all these things?
在我上船之前
You know ever since I came on board
我听说有这么一个人
I been hearing a lot of talk about a guy
他好像在船上出生
He's supposed to have been born on this ship
而且从来没下过船
and never been off it since
不可思议
Crazy story
20年从来没
Twenty years without ever
踏上陆地
setting foot on land?
27年
Twenty seven
听说这家伙做的音乐
They say this guy makes music
前无古人
that's never been heard before
我也听说过
I've heard of him too
刚开始我以为你就是
First off I thought you were the guy
但是经过这些事后
But then something didn't add up
我想  如果这位就是1900
I figured: if he's Nineteen Hundred
他怎么会熟知新奥尔良
how could he know New Orleans so well?
因为你去过那
Because you've been to New Orleans
如果我告诉你我从没去过
If I told you I'd never set foot in that town
你信吗
would you believe me?
管你是谁
Whoever you are
马克斯 托尼
Max Tooney
很高兴认识你
Gald to meet you
知道要干什么吗
How we doing?
我们要拆了这东西
We're supposed to blow it up
不要让鱼先把它给吃了
not wait for it to be eaten by the fishes
你们不能拆了它
You're not going to blow up a goddamn thing
我最好的朋友还在船上
because my best friend is on this ship
你们要承担谋杀的罪行
You'll all be responsible for murder
让他滚出去
Get him out of here!
把他给我赶出去
Do whatever you want, but get him off my case
我不是来捣乱的 我也没疯
I'm not making this up and I'm not crazy
如果我告诉你
If I tell you there's a man
有人在维吉尼亚号上
aboard the Virginian
我对天发誓
Jesus Christ
确实还有人在船上
it means there's a man aboard the Virginian
我们把船上上下下清了个遍
We cleaned that scuttle from stem to stern
连门把手都没留下
Not even doorknobs were left
只留下了炸药  炸药
Only dynamite. Dynamite
你怎么确信有人在船上
How can you be so sure that's a man on board?
如果你有证据 拿出来
If you've any proof, out with it
因为我就是那个
Because I'm the horse's arse
按下爆破按钮的人
who has to throw that switch
我确信他在那
I'm sure he's there
我人生最好的时光
I spent the best years of my life
都在维吉尼亚号上
on the Virginian
换曲了
End of line
酷 弹下去
All right! Run it down
你弹琴的时候
What the hell do you think
都在想些什么
about when you're playing?
击键时
Where does your mind go
你的思维去了哪
when you hit the keys?
昨晚我在一个美丽的村庄
Last night I was in a beautiful country
女人香气扑鼻
Women had perfume in their hair
荣光焕发
Everything glowed
还有数不尽的老虎
And it was full of tigers
他在神游
He traveled.
每次都去往不同的地方
And each time he ended up someplace different
在伦敦的中心
In the heart of London
在穿过田园的列车上
on a train in the middle of the country
在火山的边缘
on the edge of a giant volcano
在世界上最大的教堂
in the biggest church in the world
数着石柱
counting the columns
仰望着神灵
and staring up at the crucifixes
他在神游
He traveled
孩子 弹一首欢快的塔朗泰拉
Hey, Kid, give us a good tarantella
那你要告诉我什么是塔朗泰拉
And you show me how a tarantella goes paisa
美国
America
你为什么不下去
Why the hell don't you get off?
就一次  一次而已
Just once? One time?
用自己的眼睛
See the world for yourself
去看看世界
with your own eyes?
你从没想过吗
You ever think about it?
你能做任何事
You could do anything you wanted to
人们会为你而疯狂
People would go crazy for you
兄弟 你会赚很多钱
You could make beaucoup bucks, man
住最好的房子
Get yourself the finest house
找个妻子
Get yourself a wife
有什么不好
Why not?
上帝知道
God knows you
你不能把余生
can't spend the rest of your life
变得像悠游球那样来来回回
traveling back and forth like some yo-yo
世界就在那儿
The world is out there
就是一个跳板的距离
Nothing but a gangplank to cross
什么是跳板  就是几步而已
And what's a gangplank? A few stupid steps
天呀
Christ
美好的生活就几步而已
everything is waiting at the bottom of those steps
为什么不试一下
Why don't you just do it
一次
one time?
为什么就是不下去
Why don't you just get off?
为什么  为什么
Why? Why? Why? Why? Why?
陆地上的人
I think land people
浪费太多时间在为什么上
waste a lot of time wondering why
冬天害怕夏天的迟来
Winter comes and you can't wait for summer
夏天担心冬天将至
Summer comes and you live in dread of winter
这就是为什么你不会厌倦
That's way you never tire of traveling
永远在追寻着
Always chasing someplace far away
哪里永远是夏天
where it's always summer
我并不羡慕
Doesn't sound like a good bet to me
停一下 都停下
Hold it! Stop everything
请原谅我
Forgive me for allowing myself
沉醉于你的音乐之中
to your music was so strong
去美国
You don't look too happy
你不觉得高兴吗
to be going to America
不是美国的原因
It's not America
是以前的事
It's everything I leave behind
几年前我还只知道我的土地
Until a few years ago I know only my field
对我而言那狭小的土地
The world for me started and ended there
就是整个世界
in that little piece of the land
我从来没有上过街
I never walked down the main street of a city
也许你不能理解
Maybe you can't understand but
我完全能理解
I understand perfectly
我知道有人
I know someone
也有这样的经历
who went through something very similar
他的土地也干涸了
And one fine day did his field go dry too?
他的妻子也跟神父跑了
And did his wife also run off with a priest?
他的五个孩子也被病魔夺去生命
And did the fever take his five children?
没有 但是他一直都很孤独
No. But he ended up alone too
那他比我幸运
Then he is more lucky than me
我还有一个女儿  最小的
I still have a daughter The young one
她活了下来
She survived
为了她
And it's for her
有一天我决定不再坐以待毙
that I decide one day to fight against my bad luck
我四处游走  漫无目的
and travel all over without a destination
有一天
And then one day
我去了一个
when I go through
从来没去过的镇
one of the many towns I never see before
我爬上一个小山
I come to a hill
然后我见到了
And then I see
这辈子最美的东西
the most beautiful thing in my life
大海
The sea
The sea?
我从没看见过
I never see it before
听到一种声音
It was like lightning hit me
就像被闪电击中了
Because I hear the voice
大海的声音
The voice of the sea?
是 大海的声音
Yeah, the voice of the sea
我从没听过
I never heard it
大海的声音就像呼喊
The voice of the sea it is like a shout
那种大而强的呼喊
A shout big and strong
一刻不停
screaming and screaming
就好像在说
And the thing it was screaming was:
你
You
这个猪脑子
with shit instead brains
生命如此广阔  你能理解吗
life is immense can you understand that?
广阔无边
Immense
我从来没这么想过
I never think of it that way
脑袋就像被洗过了
A revolution was in my head
这就是我为什么
That's how
突然决定改变我的生活
I suddenly decide to change my life
从新来过
to start fresh
改变生活  从新来过
Change life. Start fresh
告诉你的那位朋友
Tell that to your friend
Nineteen Hundred
我是马克斯 托尼  你的朋友
It's Max Tooney, your friend
出来吧 1900
Come on out, Nineteen Hundred!
我也是你的朋友
I'm your friend too
也许从来没见过
Even if we never met
不要当心 没警察
Don't worry, no cops
你说了些钢琴的事
You said something about a piano
在哪儿
Where was it exactly?
在那发现的
We found it over there
Nineteen Hundred
你们的小提琴手  比尔 道格拉斯
On the violin yours truly, Bill Douglas
贝司手  弗雷迪  罗卡弄
Tuba and bass, Freddie Loycano
小号手 马克斯 托尼
Max Tooney on trumpet
最后 钢琴师
And finally, on piano
丹尼 博得曼 T.D. 雷蒙  1900
Danny Boodman T.D. Lemon Nineteen Hundred
最好的
the greatest
最后一次 1900 不要...
For the last time Nineteen Hundred, just...
不要给我惹麻烦
just the normal notes
开始了
End of the line
你怎么想到的
Where do yu get it?
什么
What?
灵感
The music
不知道  举个例子
I don't know. You see that woman over there
你看见那边那个女人吗
for example?
她看起来
She looks like someone
就像和她情夫一起
who's killed her husband
杀了她丈夫
with the help of her lover
现在正带着
And now she's running off
珠宝在跑路
with the family jewels
你不觉得曲子像她
Don't you think this music's her?
他妈的 没错
Damn, it's true
你看那边那个人
You see that guy over there?
他有心事
He can't forget a thing
听听他的
Listen to his music
他脑中充斥着回忆
His head bursts with memories
却无能为力
and there's nothing he can do about it
再看那个
And look at that one there
她看上去就像
She looks like a prostitute
想变成修女的妓女
who's thinking of becoming a nun
太不可思议了
That's incredible
现在看那个
Now, look at this one
看到他怎么走路了吗
See how he walks?
我说他穿了别人的衣服
I'd say he's in someone else's suit
只要看他穿的方式就知道
judging by the way he wears it
他是偷偷溜进
I'd say he's a stowaway
头等舱的
slipped into first class
寻找不可思议的爱情
Iooking for an amorous adventure
眼睛里散发着美国梦
This one's got America stamped on his eyes
我都能听见他的叫喊
I can already hear him screaming
美国
America!
我要把钱赚回来
I'm going to get my money back
就在今天
That'll be the day
单身族  李 克莱尔
Singleton, Lee Claire
你不认识我
You don't know me
但我想
But I was wondering
我们能不能聊会天
if we could have a little chat
交谈  谈些什么
A little chat? What about?
随便聊聊  就像天气情况什么的
About anything you like Weather conditions?
你可以随便挑个话题
Anything You pick or chuck the subject
这算淫秽骚扰电话?
Is this an obscene phone call?
上帝啊
Christ
你就是身价20美元的那小子?
You the fish with the twenty-dollar name?
嘿  你要上哪去  我们得谈谈
Man, where you going? We got to talk
那边
That way
等等  我们只是想和你谈谈
Wait, we just want to talk to you
你以为你是谁啊
Where the hell are we, man?
别动  你个兔崽子
Hold still you little son of a bitch
出来  我们不想伤害你
Come on out! We don't want to hurt you
我们也是演奏音乐的
We're players, man! Sidemen
挺能躲的啊
Bon appetie
你可以再说一遍  再说一遍  哥
You can say that again, brother You can say that again
你就是那个能把十种爵士融合为一种的人?
You the one that plays ten kinds of jazz rolled into one?
我从不管这些  我只是个弹钢琴的
I've never counted them I'm just a piano player
想想吧  朋友  是创造爵士乐的人让我们来这的
Better start counting, buddy. The man who invented jazz sent us here
是吗
Really?
他想要我干什么
What does he want with me?
他向你发起一场钢琴对决
He challenges you to a piano duel
杰里・罗  你为什么要乘蒸汽船环游欧洲
Jello Roll, what's the reason for a trip to Europe on a steamer
你从未上过
when you've never been on anything
比密西西比河船还要大的船吗
bigger than a Mississippi riverboat?
我可不鸟这欧洲
I don't give a damn about Europe
我上这船的唯一原因是
The only reason I'm hopping this crappy tub
因为我要见一位绅士
is because there's a gentleman I want to meet
他们说他钢琴弹得很棒
They say he plays a hot piano
但我听说他从不踏足陆地
But I hear he has a little thing about setting foot on land
他在和我说话吗
Is he talking about me?
反正他正在谈论你
You bet he's talking about you
他说  嘿  杰里
He say, Hey, Jelly
有人弹得比你更好
Someone plays better piano than you
所以我和自己说  那小子能弹得多好啊
So I say to myself, Self how can this cat play so well
他甚至都没种离开那艘屁船
when he don't even have the balls to get off the goddamn ship
嘿  大名人  杰里
Hey, hot damn, Jelly
你是爵士乐的鼻祖
You invented jazz
我是说  你只要抬起手指随便挥动下
I said, Goddamn you can afford a first-class ticket to Europe
就能负担得起
and the boat that's going to take you
一张去欧洲头等船舱的票费
just by lifting a finger Get a shot of it, boys, get a shot
说实话  你害怕吗
Tell the truth. Are you scared?
我不清楚
I don't know
为什么要对决  对决会发生些什么
Why a duel? What happens when you have a duel?
我希望杰里・罗・莫顿有他们说得那么好
I hope this Jelly Roll Morton guy is as good as they say
听说他回美国了
Heard a lot about him back in the States
他是个黑鬼
He's a Negro
我确信
I believe
你坐了我该坐的位置
you're sitting in my seat
你就是那个来弹奏爵士乐的人  对吧
You're the one who invented jazz, right?
他们都那么说
That's what they say
你就是那个
And you're the one
只在船上弹奏的家伙?  对吧
who can't play unless you have the ocean under your ass?right?
我这么说
That's what I say
(法语)
(Franch)
杰里・罗・莫顿不是在弹奏
Jelly Roll Morton did not play
他在爱抚这些音符
He caressed those notes
听起来就像丝绸划过了女人的肌肤
It sounded like a silk slip sliding down a woman's body
他的手指如蝴蝶般轻盈
His hands were butterflies so light
他开始弹奏那沁人心脾的曲子
He got his start in the famed tenderloin districts of New Orleans
当他在船厅里敲击着键盘
And did he learn to stroke the keyboard in those whorehouses
楼上原本忙碌的人们不再骚动
People doing the deed upstairs didn't want any uproar
他们想要音乐划过窗帘  流过床底
They wanted music to slip behind the curtains and under the beds
没有烦躁的情绪
without disturbing the passion
他弹奏的就是这样的音乐
That's the kind of music he played
在音乐中
And in that
他坚信自己才是天下第一
he truly was the best
好极了
Bravo!
轮到你了  水手
Your turn, sailor
加油
Come on
他在做什么
What's he doing?
《平安夜》?
"Silent Night"?
那不是耶诞颂歌吗
Isn't that a Christmas carol?
他知道这是比赛吗
Does he understand it's a contest?
《平安夜》是爵士乐?
"Silenet Night" is jazz?
圣诞不早过了吗
Is it Christmas already?
拜托  杰里・罗弹奏的才是爵士乐
Come on, Jelly Roll show us what jazz is all about
你有毛病啊
What is wrong with you?
我情不自禁的就被音乐感动得哭了
I can't help it. Music makes me cry
所有的船员把全年的报酬都赌在你身上了
The whole crew bet on you I put a year's pay on the line
现在你停下来想想你的音乐
Now you cut that out and start thinking your music
我也能来打赌吗
Can I bet too?
不行
No!
赌自己会遭厄运的
It's bad luck to bet on yourself
我不是想赌自己  我想赌他  他是最棒的了
I don't want to bet on me. I want to bet on him. He's the greatest
你疯了吧  你知道自己在干什么吗
You are crazy, you know that?
如果我输了你就能把钱拿回来
That way, if you lose you'll get your money back
是完全相同的一首曲子  亲爱的
It's exactly the same piece of music, darling
真的一模一样
This is really the end of the line
难以置信
Unbelievable
加油啊  你可以比他弹得更好的
Come on you can do better than that
杰里  让他们知道船是怎么沉的
Jelly, show them how to sink a ship
你给我好好听着
You stick this up your ass
嘿  麦克斯
Hey, Max
给我根烟  行吗
Give me a cigarette, will you?
可你连烟都拿不好啊
You're not handling this well
就给我一根烟吧
Just give me a cigarette
可你不抽烟的啊
You don't smoke
你是怎么了  你一只手就足以打败他了
What is the matter with you? You could lick this guy with one hand
去啊
Come on
你到底给不给
Are you going to give me a cigarette?
我们将要挖上几百年的煤
We'll be chucking coal a couple hundred years
而你只是说...
and all you can say is...
给我一根烟!
Give me a fucking cigarette will you?
混球  你逼我的
You asked for it, asshole
你抽吧
You smoke it
我可抽不来
I don't know how
杰里・罗・莫顿在剩下的航行时间里把自己锁在船舱内
Jelly Roll Morton spend the rest of that trip locked in his cabin
在到南安普敦时
When we got to Southampton
他离开弗吉尼亚州返回美国
he got off the Virginian and went back to America
我记得1900看着他离开码头
I remember Nineteen Hundred watched him as he walked off down the dock
他只说了句
and all he said was
去他的爵士乐
Fuck jazz too
他只是说了  去他的爵士乐
And that's just what he said "Fuck jazz too"
这是个令人难以置信的故事
This is an incredible story
我错过什么重要的东西了吗
Did I miss anything important?
可以这么说
You couldn say that
靠
Damn
别担心  他以后会告诉你  不是吗
Don't worry, our friend will fill you in later. Won't you?
你可以指望他
You can count on it
谢了  他很擅长讲故事
Thanks He's so good at telling tales
这不是故事  先生
This is no tale, sir
可没人在场
There's nobody here
因为我们人太多吓到他了
Because there's too many of us We scared him
如果你再不离开就逮捕你
You leave this ship or I'll have to have you arrested
快回去工作吧
Get back to work. Quickly
再给我一次机会吧
Give me another chance
走吧  朋友  明天中午以后这船就成历史了
Piss off, friend. Noon tomorrow this ship is history
停下  不然我就要开枪了
Stop or I'll shoot
抓到你了
Gotcha
放轻松  是我  波普斯
Pops, easy, it's me
又是你
You again?
是的  放低枪口  好吗
Yes, lower that cannon, will you?
找到你的乐器再偷走它
See your instrument and then steal it back again
又是这套老把戏  我早应该猜到你是个贼
That's an old trick. I should have guessed that you were a thief
我正在找这个
I was looking for this
你要那个干嘛
And what do you need that for?
这是生死攸关的事  我需要张照片
It's a matter of life and death And I need a phonograph too
你是贼还是骗子
A thief and a liar
波普斯  我没多少时间了
Pops I don't have a whole lot of time
是啊  因为我有枪
Well, I do! Seeing as I have a gun
我现在突然想到了这个
And now that I think of it
是在船上录制的唱片
since when were records made on board steamships
如果那首曲子是你朋友弹奏的
If that music was played by your friend
这意味着他在此生中曾下过船  对吗
it means that at some time in his life he got off that ship! Correct?
没那机会  波普斯
Not a chance, Pops
他自己一个人录制的
He cut this passionate recording personally
我认为这是他的杰作
I think it's his best work
他一秒都没下过船
But he didn't jump ship to do it not even for a second
又没人限制过1900
The sky's the limit Mr. Nineteen Hundred
我们相信他的唱片一定能畅销的
If this record sells like hotcakes and we think it will
你会大有前途的  1900先生
you'll go far, Mr. Nineteen
你介意我称呼你做1900吗
Do you mind if I call you Nineteen?
这会伤害到我的  不是吗
This is going to hurt, isn't it?
先生  请准备
Ready now, gentelmen
听我数数  1  2  3
On the count. And one, two, three
Nineteen
这首曲子真绝了  它叫什么名字
That is one amazing piece of music What is it called?
这曲子让人痴迷
It's going to have people crying buckets
它需要一个能吸引人的名字
It's got to have the right title though, something catchy like
就像《畅游清风》或者...
"Swinging in the Breeze" or...
太棒了  像这样
Great, as usual
《甜蜜的世纪乐队》  就这样
"Sweet Nineteen," that's it
你就会成为大人物
You are going to be bigtime
你所要做的只是向前跨一大步
And all you got to do is take that big step
什么一大步
What big step?
下船  离开这恶心的木船跳板
Getting off. Getting off these lousy planks of wood
接下来
and going after...
获得你应有的财富和名誉
going after your fame and fortune
虽然不一定是你梦寐以求的
I don't mean to butt in fellas, but
但只要这样就能得到任何你想要的
with this you can have anything you want
而且不再需要离开船了
and never have to set foot off this boat
我们会复制上百万的副本
We'll print millions of copies
全世界的人们
so that people all over the world
都能听到你美妙的旋律  1900
can hear your wonderful music Nineteen
1900先生
Mr. Nineteen?
我不会让我的音乐离我而去
I won't let my music go anywhere without me
不  别碰
No! Don't touch
你在干什么  你不能这样做
What are you doing? You can't do that
我们有合约在先  不许反悔
We have a contract You can't go back now
我总反悔
I always go back
小姐
Miss
我将愉快不已  如果...
I'd be pleased if...
尊敬的  小姐
Miss
我将兴奋不已
I'd be thrilled
如果你接受这个
if yu'd accept this...
小礼物
small token
帕多安小姐  你一个人在这干什么  数浪?
Miss Padoan, what are you doing here all alone? Counting the waves?
船长说我们即将穿过北回归线
The captain said we'd be passing the Tropic of Cancer soon
太棒了  我们至少有东西可以瞧瞧了
Great! At least we'll have something to look at
你注意过海是怎么变颜色的吗  一天变十次
You ever notice how the sea changes colors? Ten times a day
甚至更多
Even more
我会花上一整天看海
I could look at the sea all day long
你知道的  农民从不去看海
You know farmers don't ever look at the sea
我听说他们害怕
It scares them At least that's what I heard
那不是真的
That's not true
我爸爸曾经告诉我他听到大海的声音
Once, my father told me he heard the ocean's voice
真的吗  谁说的
Really? What did it say?
不能告诉你  这是个秘密  秘密应当要保密
I can't tell you. It's a secret And secrets should be kept
天啊  我们进屋吧  雨下得太大了
Gosh, it's really coming down now Let's get back inside
我搀着您
Let me take your arm
女寝  三层
Women's dormitory 3 class
下一个
Next
抱歉
Excuse me
借过
对不起  小姐
Please, miss
我有话想对你说
I have to talk to you
你要去见你的父亲  对吗
You're meeting your father aren't you?
是啊
Yes
你怎么知道的
How did you know?
我觉得我见过他
I think I've met him
就在这船上
On this ship
几年之前
quite a few years ago
我不知道他是不是乘了同一艘船
I don't know if he took this same ship
我确定
I'm sure of it
他有一支法国的小风笛
He has a musette
我们还一起演奏过
I think we played together
我不知道他是否还记得
I don't know if he'd remember, but
请代我向他问声好
say hello to him
我会的
I will
但你怎么会知道我是谁  很奇怪  不是吗
But how did you know who I was? It's very strange, no?
这是个秘密
It's a secret
秘密应当要保密
And secrets should be kept
尽管我认为你父亲回去后会有不同想法
Although I think your father felt differently back then
请接受这个
Please accept this...
音乐的小礼物
small musical token
对不起  我听不到
I'm sorry, but I can't hear you
我想要你...
I want you to...
接受这份小礼物
accept this small token
我听不到你在说什么
I can't hear you
祝你好运
Good luck
谢谢  也祝你好运
Thank you. Good luck to you too
你为什么不来我们这儿
Why don't you come and visit us some day?
我们住在莫特街27号
We live on Mott Street. Number 27
我爸爸有开了家鱼店
My father has a fish shop
可能会来吧
Maybe
好的  帕多安  下一个
Padoan, okay. Next
下一个
Next
他再也没有提起她  我也没再问他
He never mentioned her to me again And I never asked
至少是后来的12年里
At least not for the next twelve crossings
此外  他快乐依旧
Besides, he was happy just like always
他的名气到达了顶峰
His popularity was its peak
然后  某个春天的晚上
Then, one evening in spring
在途经热那亚到纽约的路上
halfway between Genoa and New York right it the middle of the ocean
到达纽约的三天前
In three days when we get to New York
我要离开这船
I'm getting off this ship
怎么不说话了
Cat got your tongue?
不  我很高兴
No,I'm glad
怎么会这么突然
But all of a sudden?
兄弟啊...
My man...
你终于开窍了
That's aces
我想要看些东西
I've got to see something down there
看什么
What?
大海
The ocean
你开玩笑呢吧
You're pulling my leg
自从你出生那天起
You've seen nothing but the ocean
你就一直对着海着呢
since the day you were born
只从船上看过啊
But from here
我想从陆地上看看海的样子
I want to see it from there
换个角度  和从船上看根本就是两码事
It's not the same thing at all
那你就等我们靠岸的时候
Wait till we dock lean over the side
好好看看吧
take a good look
其实都一样
It's the same thing
不  不一样的
No, it's not
在岸上  你是可以听到大海的声音的
From land, you can hear its voice
那是一种无法从船上听到的声音
You don't hear that from a ship
什么叫"大海的声音"啊
What do you mean, its voice?
大海的声音
Its voice
就像...
It's like...
就像是一声震耳欲聋的惊叫
a big scream...
像对生命的广博的惊叹
telling you that life is immense
一旦你聆听过这样的声音  你就会知道
Once you've heard it, then you know
怎么样才有继续生活下去的动力和激情
what you have to do to go on living
虽然我可以永远待在船上
I could stay here forever
但这样大海是不会给我任何启示的
But the ocean would never tell me a thing
倘若我下船  去陆地上感受几年  生活几年
But if I get off live on land for a couple of years
我就会是正常的了
then I'll be normal
像其他人一样
just like the others
然后或许有一天
Then maybe one day
我会到海岸边去  仰望大海  瞧瞧它的样子
I'll make it to the coast look up, see the ocean
然后聆听大海的咆哮
and hear it scream
我不知道这些乱七八糟的都是谁告诉你的
I don't know who's been telling you this bullshit
或者是你自己莫名其妙的想出来的
or if you're just making it up
但是你想知道我的想法吗
But you want to know what I think?
我的想法就是...
I think...
真正让你有下船的冲动的原因  是那个女孩
the real reason you want off this ship is the girl
只有那个女孩是你想下船的原因
It's always the girl
但就算不是这个原因的话我也无所谓
But even if it's not the reason that suits me just fine
因为我一直都想让你离开这艘船
Because I've always wanted you to leave this ship
为陆地上的观众演奏
and play for the people on land
然后再娶个好妻子  成家立业  儿孙满堂
and marry a nice woman and have children
我希望你能拥有的是那些生命中不那么"广博"的
and all those things in life which are not immense
但却是值得你为之奋斗的
but are worth the effort
你会来看我吧  麦克斯  去陆地上我的家
You'll come visit me won't you, Max? On land?
当然了
Of course
我去看你的时候  你要向我介绍
That way, you'll introduce me
你孩子的母亲
to the mother of your children
还要邀请我和你们一起共进星期日的晚餐
And invite me for Sunday dinner
我会带些甜点外加一瓶酒
I'll bring the dessert and a bottle of wine
然后你就会对我说用不着这么客气
and you'll tell me I shouldn't have
当你向我介绍带着我参观
and while you're showing me around
你那所建的似船一样的房子
your house shaped like a ship
你妻子在为大家烤火鸡
your wife will be cooking a turkey
然后我们都会坐在桌旁
And then we'll sit at the table
我会夸赞她的厨艺
and I'll tell her she's an excellent cook
她会对我说你总会对她提起有关于我的事
and she'll say how you talk about me all the time
知道么  我打算把我的骆驼大衣送你了
You know I'm going to give you my camel coat
等你下船的时候你穿着它肯定特帅
You'll cut a fine figure when you get down there
我见过无数次人们在
How many people I have seen
在码头上互相道别之后却
saying goodbye on the docks
立即转身离去  神色漠然
without giving a damn
但是当我与1900到了说再见的时候
But when I said goodbye to Nineteen Hundred
道别却成了最伤感的事情
it was a real blow
虽然我们互相笑着说"回见"
We laughed and kept saying "See you soon"
但是我们都心知肚明  分离即永别
But inside we both knew we'd never see each other again
再见了  1900  多保重
Goodbye, Nineteen Hundred! Take care
祝你好运  好好玩
Good luck Have a good time
保重  1900  千万保重
Take care Nineteen Hundred, take care
时不时地给我们写信啊
Write us a letter sometimes
代我向百老汇问好啊
Give my regards to Broadway
他怎么了  踩着屎了不成
What'd he do, step in shit?
说不定他忘拿什么东西了吧
Maybe he just forgot something
也有可能忘了为何下船
Maybe he's forgotten why he's getting off
你想怎么样
What do you want?
从那以后  很长一段时间  他都怪怪的
He was strange for a long time after that
不跟任何人讲话
He wouldn't talk to anyone
一天一天  沉默寡言
He preferred keeping to himself for days and days
他似乎沉浸在了某件心事中
He seemed taken by very personal matters
然后有一天  当我坐在酒吧里的时候
Then one day while I was sitting at the bar
谢谢你的大衣了  麦克斯  很合身
Thanks for the coat, Max.Fit like a glove
上次太可惜了
It was a real shame
现在感觉好多了  我不再想着下船的事了
I'm much better now I'm done with all that
仿若时光倒流啊
Just like old times
1933年8月21日  我离开了维珍尼亚号
I left the Virginian on August 21st, 1933
我拿着我的离开文件和被拖欠薪水  就这么离开了
with my leave papers and back pay everything in order
我知道自己迟早会
I knew that sooner or later
结束我的海上生活的
I'd have been through with the ocean
所以我决定开始我的陆上生活
So that's what I did
我再也没有听说过任何
I heard no more about
有关于1900或维珍尼亚号的消息
Nineteen Hundred or the Virginian
但我从未忘却他们
Not that I ever forgot them
反而
On the contrary
战争期间的时候我总会问自己
During the war I'd always ask myself
谁知道如果1900在的话
Who knows what Nineteen Hundred would do
他会怎么做呢
if he were here?
说些什么
Who knows what he'd say?
也许他会说"去他妈的战争"吧
Fuck war, he'd say
但这话从一我这说出口就变味了
But said by me it wasn't the same thing
时过境迁了  懂吗
A lot of time's gone by, you know
谁敢说他真的从没下过船呢
who's to say he really didn't leave
说不定他真的去过那家卖鱼的店里
Maybe he actually went to the fish shop
问候过那个女人呢
and asked for that woman
说不定吧
Maybe
你怎么了  晕船吗
What's the matter? You lose your sea legs?
你到底在哪找到那张唱片的
Where the hell did you find that record?
这些年你都做什么了
What have you been up to all these years
创造音乐
Making music
甚至战争时期也在做吗
Even during the war?
即使再也没人跳舞的时候
Even when no one was dancing anymore
即使炸弹四处飞的时候
Even when the bombs were falling
我一直都在演奏  没有停歇
And I kept playing
直到船驶到了这里
till the ship got here
你还叫它船啊
Call this a ship?
这东西比起船更像是个装满炸药即将爆炸的山
It's more like a mountain of dynamite about to explode
你不觉得有点危险吗
A bit dangerous, don't you think?
你呢  麦克斯
And you, Max?
你的小号呢
Where's your trumpet?
我很久以前就不吹小号了
I gave it up as well, as while back
但是  你知道  现在我又想重新开始吹了
But, you know, now I'm in the mood for starting again
现在我脑袋里全是新点子
I'm busting with new ideas
咱们一起组个二重奏吧  你和我
Let's start a duo. You and me
或者组个我们自己的乐队
Or our own band
乐队名就叫  丹尼 博德曼
The Danny Boodman
T.D・雷蒙 1900 大乐队怎么样
T.D. Lemon Nineteen Hundred Big Band
这名字让人热血沸腾吧
It's gets the blood going
我们肯定会特别火
We'd be a smash
来吧  1900  和我一起  我们下船吧
Come on, Nineteen Hundred Come with me. Let's get off
我们可以在码头那看烟花
We'll watch the fireworks from the pier
然后我们从零开始
and then we'll start from scratch
有时候从零开始是必要的
Sometimes that's the way you have to do it
你得回到起点
You go right back to the beginning
这并不是结束
You're never really done for...
除非你有了一段可以拿出去讲给他人听的故事才是结束
as long as you've got a good story and someone to tell it to
记得吗
Remember?
那是你告诉我的
You told me that
看吧  你现在的故事可真是都可以写成一本书了
Well, what a stack of stories you got now
全世界都会对你的每一个字洗耳恭听的
The world would be hanging on your every word
世界会为你的音乐而疯狂
crazy for your music
相信我
Believe me
整座城市
All that city
你根本无法看到它的尽头
You just couldn't see an end to it
尽头
The end...
拜托
please?
你能告诉我哪里才是城市的尽头吗
You please just show me where it ends?
在跳板上我还觉得自己很好  一切都还好
It was all very fine on that gangway. And I was grand too
穿着我的那件大衣
in my overcoat
我确实看起来很有型
I cut quite a figure
然后我确实打算要下去
And I was getting off
我发誓
Guaranteed
那并不是我最终回身上船的原因
That's wasn't the problem
并不是我所看到的让我停下了脚步  麦克斯
It wasn't what I saw that stopped me, Max
让我停下脚步的是我所没有看到的
It was what I didn't see
明白吗
Understand?
我所看不到的
What I didnt' see
城市里纵横交错的街道
In all that srawling city
除了尽头  什么都有
there was everything except an end
那里没有尽头
There was no end
我所看不到的是
What I did not see was
我下船之后的未来
was where the whole thing came to an end
我看不到世界的尽头
The end of the world
用钢琴打比方
You take a piano
钢琴键就是
Keys begin
有始有终的
The keys end
你也很清楚明了的知道钢琴一共有88个键
You know there are 88 of them
没有人能对此提出异议
Nobody can tell you any different
没有无限的因素在里面
They are not infinite
你才是那个无限的因素的主导
You are infinite
在那些琴键上
And on those keys
你演奏出来的音乐才有万千变化
the music that you can make is infinite
我喜欢这样
I like that
我只能过这样的生活
That I can live by
你把我弄到那个跳板上
You get me up on that gangway
然后你突然在我面前扔了一个
and you roll out in front of me
上面有着万千琴键的键盘
a keyboard of millions and billions of keys that never end
这就是我不能下船的原因  麦克斯
and that's the truth Max
是因为他们无穷无尽
that they never end
那个键盘本身就是无穷无尽的
That keyboard is infinite
而如果键盘是无穷无尽的话
And if that keyboard is infinite
那么在上面演奏音乐是不可能的
then there is no music you can play
你根本就没有站在合适的位置上
You're sitting on the wrong bench
那是上帝的钢琴
That's God's piano
天啊  你看到那些街道了吗  只是街道
Christ, did you see the streets? Just the streets.
就有成百上千条
There were thousands of them
你如何能在那里生活
How do you do it down there?
你如何从那么多中间选择
How do you choose just one?
一个女人
One woman
一幢房子
One house
一小块你可以看着的称之为
One piece of land to call
自己的风景的土地
your own one landscape to look at
还有一种死亡的方式
one way to die?
那整个世界都只是重压在你身上
All that world just weighing down on you
你甚至不知道什么时候才是结束  是尽头
You don't even know where it comes to an end
我是说  难道你从来都没害怕自己会
I mean, aren't you ever just scared of
因为想到这个就崩溃吗
breaking apart at the thought of it?
甚至只是想想生活在其中  就不寒而栗吗
At the enormity of living it?
我是生在这艘船上的
I was born on this ship
我已经和这个世界擦身而过了
And the world passed me by
但是每次这里都会容纳两千人
But two thousand people at a time
而且还承载了人们的愿望
And there were wishes here
但是没有比船头和船尾之间更适合的了
But never more than fit between prow and stern
你演奏出了自己的快乐幸福
You played out your happiness
但那是在一架有始有终的钢琴上
but on a piano that was not infinite
那就是我所学会的生活方式
I learned to live that way
陆地
Land?
陆地对我来说是一艘太大的船
Land is a ship too big for me
是一个太过于美丽的女人
It's a woman too beautiful
是一段太长的航程
It's a voyage too long
是太过于浓烈的香水
perfume too strong
是我不会弹奏的曲子
It's music I don't know how to make
我永远都不能离开这艘船
I could never get off this ship
最不济
At best
我还能退出生命的舞台
I can step off my life
毕竟
After all
我不为任何人而存在
I don't exist for anyone
你是例外  麦克斯
You're the exception, Max
你是唯一知道我在这里的人
You're the only one who knows I'm here
你是少数
You're a minority
而且你最好习惯它
And you'd better get used to it
原谅我  我的朋友
Forgive me, my friend
我是不会下船的
but I'm not getting off
麦克斯
Hey, Max
想像一下在天国的门前
Picture the scene at the Golden Gates
有个人看着名单  试图找到我的名字
Some guy searching a list trying to find my name
却找不到
not finding it
"再说一遍你叫什么"
What did you say your name was again?
Nineteen Hundred
尼曼  南丁格尔   纳音斯达克...
Niemann, Nightingale, Ninestock...
尼齐丁
Nittledeen?
你看  先生  我是在船上出生的
Well, you see, sir I was born on a ship
你说什么
Beg your pardon?
我在船上生  在船上长  在船上结束生命
Born, raised, and died on a ship
说不定你的册子里没我的名字
Maybe I'm not registered there
你是死在船上的
Shipwreck?
六吨半的炸药炸的
Six and a half tons of dynamite Boom
现在感觉好多了吧
Feeling better now?
是啊  感觉还不错  除了少了条胳膊
Yeah, I'm fine except I lost an arm
少胳膊
An arm?
对  炸飞了
Yes, in the explosion
没事  你能在那找到条新胳膊
Well, you should be able to find one over there
你少了哪条胳膊
Which one did you say you were missing?
左边的  先生
Left, sir
十分抱歉
I'm dreadfully sorry
我们这里似乎只剩下两条右胳膊了
we only seem to have two rights
只有两条右胳膊
Two right arms?
恐怕是这样
Afraid so
你介不介意如果...
Would you mind awfully if...
如果我什么
If I what?
如果你能接受用一条右胳膊替代左边的
Well, if you take a right arm instead of a left?
那么  好像就算只有右胳膊也比
Well, all things considered better
什么都没有强  我想是这样
a right arm than nothing, I suppose
双手赞成
Couldn't agree more
笑也没用  麦克斯
No laughing matter, Max
糟糕啊
What a cock-up
下辈子得一直过只有两条右胳膊的生活
Spend eternity with two right arms?
我说  你要怎么用胳膊做出十字的形状啊
I mean, how would you make the sign of the cross?
麦克斯
Hey, Max
想象一下我用两条右胳膊弹奏的钢琴曲吧
Imagine the music I could play with two right arms
希望我能在上面找着架钢琴
Hope I can find a piano up there
如果你是我要怎么办
What would you have done in my shoes?
我不知道
I don't know
不会觉得自己这么没用
I wouldn't probably have felt quite useless
迟早  所有的故事总会有一个结局的
Sooner or later, all stories end
然后就再也没有可以添加的东西
and there's nothing left to add
不管怎样  谢谢了
Anyhow, thanks, pops
康
Conn
有一件事我不明白
There's just one thing I don't get
是谁把坏掉的唱片藏在钢琴里的
Who hid the broken record inside the piano?
那人远在天边  近在眼前啊
You're looking at him
那你还不是一点都没用啊
So you weren't so useless after all
康
Conn
给
Here
把你的小号带走吧
Take your trumpet
你会需要的
Well, you'll be needing it
别担心  不要钱
Never mind the money
一个好故事比这个旧小号值多了
A good story's worth more than an old trumpet
谢谢
Okay, pops